<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pindarique ode, describing the excellency of true virtue, with reflexions on the satyr against virtue</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28127</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831921</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207413</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248498422</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2252A_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831921</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831921e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2130:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pindarique ode, describing the excellency of true virtue, with reflexions on the satyr against virtue</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Juvenal. --  Satura 10 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Virtue --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207413:1"/>
            <p>A PINDARIQUE ODE, DESCRIBING THE EXCELLENCY OF TRUE VIRTUE, WITH REFLEXIONS ON THE <hi>Satyr against Virtue.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Semita certe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tranquillae per VIRTUTEM patet unica Vitae.</hi>
               </l>
               <bibl>Juven. <hi>Sat.</hi> 10.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ode">
            <pb facs="tcp:207413:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207413:2"/>
            <head>A PINDARIQUE ODE, Describing the Excellency of True <hi>VIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TƲE;</hi> with Reflections on the <hi>SATYR</hi> Against VIRTUE.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>(1.)</head>
               <l>SO Vast is <hi>VIRTUES</hi> Empire, that its Power</l>
               <l>Commands a <hi>Tribute</hi> from the Worst of things;</l>
               <l>Ev'n from the Shades of <hi>Conquer'd VICE</hi> there springs</l>
               <l>A greater Light to ev'ry Soul,</l>
               <l>That can controul</l>
               <l>Those <hi>Raging PASSIONS</hi> which dark Souls <hi>devour.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>(2)</head>
               <l>A <hi>VIRTUOUS</hi> man slays Ev'ry Day</l>
               <l>In his own Breast,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Lion</hi> much more fierce than that which <hi>SAMSON</hi> slew;</l>
               <l>And from this <hi>Lion</hi> slain, there comes forth <hi>Sweetness</hi> too:</l>
               <l>When he shall pass his Days, and climb</l>
               <l>Beyond the Bounds of Time,</l>
               <l>Up to <hi>ETERNITY;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:207413:3"/>
               <l>Then <hi>Full</hi> his <hi>Joy</hi> shall be,</l>
               <l>And never shall decay:</l>
               <l>His <hi>Toilsome</hi> Fights shall end in Everlasting Rest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>(3)</head>
               <l>The
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">The <hi>Stagirite</hi> be damn'd, &amp;c. Sat, against <hi>Virtue,</hi> Stanza 1.</note>
                  <hi>Stagirite</hi> had but a Glimpse o'th' Light,</l>
               <l>Which shines in <hi>VIRTUES</hi> Glorious Face.</l>
               <l>His Notions were like <hi>Twinkling Stars</hi> i'th' <hi>Night;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But those are <hi>Sun-Beams</hi> which proceed from <hi>Grace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n from the sence of His Almighty <hi>LOVE,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who for us here was <hi>Griev'd</hi> and <hi>Slain,</hi> though still He had</l>
               <l>An Heart most <hi>Glad,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Endless Life</hi> above.</l>
               <l>Those Christians who for Him Meekly gave up their Breath</l>
               <l>Were not
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <l>When Christian Fools were obstinately good,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet their Gospel-Freedom understood,</l>
                     <l>Tame easie Fops, &amp;c. 4.</l>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tame Fops,</hi> but Bravely they did Triumph over Death,</l>
               <l>That <hi>King of Terrors,</hi> who</l>
               <l>Makes all the World to Bow;</l>
               <l>Whose Scepter all men dread, but they alone</l>
               <l>Whom he's forc'd to <hi>Transport</hi> to an Eternal <hi>CROWN.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>(4)</head>
               <l>Great <hi>SOCRATES,</hi> who as that
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Justin Martyr.</note>
                  <hi>Father</hi> says,</l>
               <l>In part our <hi>SAVIOUR</hi> knew,</l>
               <l>Deserv'd Immortal Praise;</l>
               <l>The mad <hi>Athenians</hi> murder'd him, but could not him <hi>subdue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Day he took the Fatal Draught, how did his mighty Soul</l>
               <l>Reign and Controul,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207413:3"/>
               <l>As Slaves, and Vassals, all th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Potentates;</l>
               <l>His Bright Discourse quite chang'd the hue o'th' <hi>Black</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And Dreadful <hi>Fates;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Friends look'd sad and pale as</l>
               <l>Death, but He</l>
               <l>Who was to <hi>die</hi> still talk'd of <hi>Immortalitie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis clear he never was a
<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                     <l>That Sniveling Puritan, who in spight of all the Mode,</l>
                     <l>Would be unfashionably good &amp;c. 4.</l>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Sniv'ling Puritan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Amongst that <hi>stubborn Sect</hi> ther's not a man</l>
               <l>Will ever plead his Cause,</l>
               <l>Who
<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Quidnam vero Leges dixerint; O <hi>Socrates,</hi> nonne inter nos &amp; te illud convenit, ut Judiciis stares, quae constitueret, stabiliretque Civitas? <hi>Plato</hi> in <hi>Critone.</hi>
                  </note> rather chose to die than break his Countreys Laws.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>(5.)</head>
               <l>Those <hi>Heathen Gods</hi> thou nam'st,</l>
               <l>Whose Vices thou proclaim'st,</l>
               <l>Made <hi>VIRTUE</hi> in those Dayes</l>
               <l>Deserve the greater Praise,</l>
               <l>That press'd with such Temptations, she her drooping Head could raise.</l>
               <l>How brave a Soul then had our <hi>SOCRATES!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who, 'mongst those Men, whose Gods were Patrons of all Vice</l>
               <l>Intemperance and Avarice,</l>
               <l>Of Theft, and ev'ry foul</l>
               <l>Distemper of the Soul,</l>
               <l>Declar'd that man's best Part no Earthly thing can <hi>please:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That th' Heav'n-Born Mind</l>
               <l>Can never be at rest, till it shall find</l>
               <l>A BEAUTY, which can ne'r be seen by Mortal Eyes:</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:207413:4"/>
               <l>That then the Soul <hi>lives best,</hi> when she</l>
               <l>From Commerce with the Flesh is Free:</l>
               <l>That th' Wicked can't a Good man <hi>Hurt</hi> by all that they</l>
               <l>Can ever Do, or Say;</l>
               <l>Whatever <hi>Storms</hi> About him rise, he sees a <hi>Pleasant Day.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>(6)</head>
               <l>There are no <hi>Sweets</hi> in Vice, unless it be</l>
               <l>More pleasant to turn <hi>Scabs</hi> to <hi>Wounds</hi> by scratching <hi>eagerly;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Than from all <hi>Itch</hi> and <hi>Scabs</hi> to have our Bodies free.</l>
               <l>Ah, <hi>VIRTUE,</hi> that thy Sweet Embrace were better known!</l>
               <l>Who would not less esteem a Crown,</l>
               <l>Than the Enjoyment of thy Beauteous Face,</l>
               <l>In which shines <hi>Ev'ry Grace</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>True,</hi> and <hi>Substantial!</hi> Other Beauties are</l>
               <l>But the least <hi>Shadows</hi> of what's <hi>TRULY FAIR.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O, whilst thy
<note n="(f)" place="bottom">While my plump Veins are fill'd with Lust and Blood, &amp;c. Stanza 5.</note>
                  <hi>Veins</hi> are <hi>plump,</hi> and full of <hi>Blood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strive to be <hi>Eminently</hi> good;</l>
               <l>As high as Heaven be thy Aims!</l>
               <l>Ah see! Oppressed <hi>VIRTUE</hi> claims</l>
               <l>Thy best Endeavours to support her Cause,</l>
               <l>And to restore some Reverence to her Despised Laws;</l>
               <l>Let thy Youth's Fire</l>
               <l>Make thee aspire</l>
               <l>To all thats truly Great, and see</l>
               <l>Thou never be</l>
               <l>Deceiv'd with those Proud, Stately Fops, who Earthly things admire.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:207413:4"/>
            <lg>
               <head>(7.)</head>
               <l>All Quiet sure, and Peace of Mind,</l>
               <l>Within the Bounds of <hi>VIRTUE</hi> is confin'd:</l>
               <l>Without her all that Mortals can attain</l>
               <l>Is Misery and Pain,</l>
               <l>Or th' empty shew of Joyes:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                     <q>
                        <l>Her Quiet calm and Peace of Mind</l>
                        <l>In Wine, and better Company we find,</l>
                        <l>Find it with Pleasure too combin'd</l>
                        <l>In mighty Wine, where we our Senses steep,</l>
                        <bibl>Stanza 6.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>And lull our Care and Consciences asleep.</l>
               <l>Wine does but make men Mad, and Company makes Noise:</l>
               <l>But all this Noise cann't drown the voice of <hi>Conscience,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which after some <hi>Suspence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like Thunder through the Clouds, breaks forth with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter force,</l>
               <l>Through the Condens'd Black Vapors of the Mind:</l>
               <l>And straight bold Sinners find</l>
               <l>Great cause of sharp Remorse</l>
               <l>By those bright <hi>Sparks</hi> of mighty Truth, which like to <hi>Lightning flie;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And do not <hi>chear</hi> Souls fix'd in Sin, but only <hi>Terrifie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>(8)</head>
               <l>That great <hi>Triumvirate</hi> in Sin</l>
               <l>Have in these evil Days great Rivals of their Fame,</l>
               <l>Men Glory in their Shame,</l>
               <l>And from the greatest Crimes they hope the greatest</l>
               <l>Praise to win.</l>
               <l>'Tis counted Brave to Kill the Just,</l>
               <l>In Vindication of the Basest Lust.</l>
               <l>Some Swear, and Drink, and Whore,</l>
               <l>And some that blame them, Lie, and Cheat, and never will Restore</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:207413:5"/>
               <l>Ill-gotten Goods: <hi>Hypocrisie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Contends to be</l>
               <l>Esteem'd th' Exemplar of true <hi>Puritie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some strive t'effect the Murder of their KING,</l>
               <l>Whom God Protects maugre their Spight,</l>
               <l>And secret Might,</l>
               <l>And all the Hidden Aid, that <hi>HELLS Dark Powers</hi> can bring.</l>
               <l>But, Ah dear <hi>VIRTUE,</hi> whither art thou gone?</l>
               <l>Where is that <hi>Genius,</hi> which thought thee alone</l>
               <l>Sufficient to make up True Happiness</l>
               <l>Without the Aid of <hi>Wealth,</hi> or <hi>Honours</hi> Gawdy <hi>Dress?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Return, Return; and make this Land to see,</l>
               <l>Which is so given up to Sport and Luxury,</l>
               <l>And to the <hi>Hellish Art</hi> of studied Villany,</l>
               <l>That there is no True Joy but in the LOVE of Thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>(9)</head>
               <l>O that we could be so sincerely Good,</l>
               <l>As to erase the Impress of all Ills</l>
               <l>Which our <hi>First Parent</hi> stampt on his Posterity.</l>
               <l>O that our <hi>Wills</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which their own Satisfaction ever have withstood,</l>
               <l>Might now be wholly bent on the <hi>INFINITY</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of that which our Immense Desires can Satisfie.</l>
               <l>That all the VVorld may see</l>
               <l>VVe are Heav'ns Progeny;</l>
               <l>VVhilst our Enlarged Spirits rise</l>
               <l>So high, as to Despise</l>
               <l>All things but what we may attain</l>
               <l>In larger measures by sad <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Pain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But hold, my Muse! what I was shewing, none</l>
               <l>Can comprehend, but they that have it of their own.</l>
               <l>"Thy high-flown Thoughts by <hi>VIRTUOUS</hi> Actions shew;</l>
               <l>"They Like what's <hi>Good,</hi> that can't Judge what is <hi>True.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>